A Guide to the Records of the Barrett Day Care Center 1977-1989
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Records of the Barrett Day Care Center 1977-1989
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
3283-d
The collection contains ca 520 items (3 Hollinger boxes, 1.5 linear feet).
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was given to the Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library by Leroy Hamlett, Jr. on February 27, 2002.
Biographical/Historical Information
Day care center for African-American children in Charlottesville, Va. Founded in 1935 as Janie Porter Barrett Day Nursery under the Works Progress Administration of the Education Department by Mrs. Daisy V. Green, a registered nurse from Petersburg, Va.; name changed to Barret Day Care Center on April 19, 1971.
Scope and Content
The collection contains ca 520 items (3 Hollinger boxes, 1.5 linear feet) of documents relating to the administration, organization and operation of the Barrett Day Care Center from 1977 to 1989. There are documents on accounts that were outstanding, annual reports; applications for employment and job descriptions; applications for funding and fundraising; bank information; bills for payment by the Barrett Day Care Center; Board of Directors meetings and minutes; a list of donors and their letters; events and schedules; Federal Child Care Proposals, and financial statements. There are also insurance records; investment funds; literature, legal name changes, by-laws, information on committees, and publications; regulations, including responsibilities of the teachers, background checks, revised personnel procedures, evaluation forms, handbooks, and curricula; tax returns; teacher contracts, complaints, and law suits; United Way Scholarships; and a USDA Audit report with correspondence regarding a discrepancy in milk funds.
There is also a Needs and Assessment Survey and its findings for the Garrett Square Day Care Center (later named Molly Michie Infant Care Center); Garrett Square Proposals containing lease revisions and correspondence with the city of Charlottesville and organizations such as the Central Virginia Child Development Association, and the United Way; There are letters about legal issues surrounding the building and the landlord; documents and correspondence relating to the opening and operation of the Mollie Michie Infant Care Center (formerly named the Garrett Square Day Care Center). There are documents including letters about visits from licensing specialists and fulfillment of Federal Register New Day Care Requirements, (Title XX standards), as well as funding information. There is also a billing statement for an oil painting of Mrs. Mollie Michie, a dedication ceremony announcement and an organization chart.
The collection has several miscellaneous items such as a letter from the Virginia Historic Landmark Commission to nominate Ridge Street as a historic district,a letter from the Barrett Parents Organization to Mayor Laurence Brunton protesting the widening of Ridge Street, letters regarding repairs and maintenance of the Centers, an accident report, resignation letters, employee check stubs, thank you letters and unrelated personal correspondence of staff.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in one series, the records of the Barrett Day Care Center. The records are organized alphabetically by topic and chronologically within each folder
Contents List
- Accounts Outstanding 1978-1986 (Box-folder 1:1)
- Annual Reports 1978-1981;1983-1986 (Box-folder 1:2)
- Applications for employment, and job descriptions 1979-1988 (Box-folder 1:3)
- Applications for funding and fund-raising 1978; 1982-1983; 1986-1988 (Box-folder 1:4)
- Bank n.d.; 1981-1985 (Box-folder 1:5)
- Bills for payment by Barrett Day Care Center 1976-1985 (Box-folder 1:6)
- Board of Directors 1978-1981 (Box-folder 1:7)
- Board of Directors 1982-1989 (Box-folder 1:8)
- Donations 1979; n.d. (Box-folder 1:9)
- Events and schedules 1981; 1985; 1987-1989 (Box-folder 1:10)
- Federal Child Care Proposals 1988 (Box-folder 1:11)
- Financial statements 1979-1983 (Box-folder 1:12)
- Financial statements 1984-1989 (Box-folder 1:13)
- Garrett Square Day Care Needs Assessment Survey 1979 (Box-folder 2:1)
- Garrett Square Day Care Center Proposals, Leases, By-Laws 1978-1979;1984 (Box-folder 2:2)
- Insurance 1975-1987 (Box-folder 2:3)
- Investment Funds 1979; 1982 (Box-folder 2:4)
- Literature n.d. 1986 (Box-folder 2:5)
- Miscellaneous 1977-1988 (Box-folder 2:6)
- Molly Michie Infant Care Center 1979-1981 (Box-folder 2:7)
- Regulations 1978-1988 (Box-folder 2:8)
- Tax Returns 1978-1982 (Box-folder 2:9)
- Tax Returns 1983-1987 (Box-folder 2:10)
- Teacher contracts and issues (lawsuits) 1977-1978 (Box-folder 3:1)
- United Way Scholarship Committee and Payment Schedules 1978-1980 (Box-folder 3:2)
- U.S.D.A Audit Report 1982-1984 (Box-folder 3:3)